Guide to the Russell Lee Collection
The Wittliff Collections
- Photographs by Russell Lee, circa 1936-1961
  - Standard Oil New Jersey / Aramco, 1949-1981
    - Oil exploration, Saudi Arabia [shot for Aramco], 1955 (Box 19, Item WG329)
    - Arabia [shot for Aramco], circa 1955 (Box 19, Item WG331)
    - Arabia [shot for Aramco], circa 1955 (Box 19, Item WG332)
    - Brazil, Adjacento Field, Making up Flight Plan, 1944, 1981 (Box 19, Item WG382)
  - Italy, 1960
    - Modena, Italy, 1960 (Box 19, Item WG334)
    - View of Matera, Italy, 1960 (Box 19, Item WG335)
    - Melissa (Calabria, Italy), 1960 (Box 19, Item WG335a)
    - Neapolitan holiday-makers on Easter Monday, Caserta, 1960 (Box 19, Item WG336)
    - Festival near Rome [cropped], 1960 (Box 19, Item WG337)
  - Post-World War II Texas, 1950-1960
    - [Young girl on steps at] Children's Concert, Austin, Texas, circa 1950-1955 (Box 19, Item WG338)
    - J. Frank Dobie at Joe Small's BBQ [cropped], 1957 (Box 19, Item WG340)
    - J. Frank Dobie at Joe Small's BBQ [cropped, facing camera], 1957 (Box 19, Item WG340a)
    - J. Frank Dobie smoking pipe possibly at Joe Small's BBQ [writing on paper, next to older unidentified man], 1957 (Box 19, Item WG340b)
    - Fred Gipson, circa 1950-1960 (Box 19, Item WG341)
    - [Walter Johnson at the Texas Cowboy Reunion] Stamford, Texas, 1959 (Box 19, Item WG342)
    - Hart Stillwell [in Texas], circa 1950-1960 (Box 19, Item WG343)
    - Rockdale, Texas, circa 1950 (Box 19, Item WG345)
    - Rockdale, Texas, circa 1950 (Box 19, Item WG346)
    - Children at symphony concert, Austin, Texas, circa 1955 (Box 19, Item WG347)
    - Children at symphony concert, Austin, Texas, circa 1955 (Box 19, Item WG348)
    - Spanish speaking father and child, San Angelo, Texas, 1949 (Box 19, Item WG349)
    - Spanish speaking father and child, San Angelo, Texas, 1949 (Box 19, Item WG350)
    - Double muggers waiting for their turn at the rodeo [at the Texas Cowboy Reunion], Stamford, Texas, 1959 (Box 19, Item WG351)
    - Double muggers waiting for their turn at the rodeo [at the Texas Cowboy Reunion], Stamford, Texas, 1959 (Box 19, Item WG352)
    - San Angelo, Texas [young girl with elbow on table, head resting on hand], 1949 (Box 19, Item WG354)
    - Truck driver [with cowboy boots sticking out of truck window], Vernon, Texas, 1949 (Box 19, Item WG355)
    - Couple [Milton and Vernell] at Gillespie County Fair, Texas, 1958 (Box 19, Item WG356)
    - Ladies talking together at Fourth of July celebration, Belton, Texas, 1956 (Box 19, Item WG357)
    - Mrs. Rafaela Cortez and grandchild, Corpus Christi, Texas, 1949 (Box 19, Item WG358)
    - A patient in isolation for her protection at State Institution for the Elderly, Terrell, Texas, 1959 (Box 19, Item WG359)
    - [Child at] Texas State School, Austin, Texas, 1959 (Box 19, Item WG360)
    - Maximum security ward for criminally insane, Rusk State Hospital, Texas. Tranquilizers are used to keep patients quiet and docile, circa 1959 (Box 19, Item WG361)
    - [Three cowboys in chaps sitting under a tarp at the Fat Stock Show, Austin], circa 1956 (Box 19, Item WG362)
    - From Russell Lee's notes:] County groups as they held conferences with [Ralph] Yarborough in his hotel room after the main meeting in the Cap Rock Hotel where about 300 or 350 were in attendance, circa 1950-1960 (Box 19, Item WG363)
  - FSA Photographs, 1940-1954
    - Log cabin occupied by a farmer and his family, McIntosh County, Oklahoma, 1940 (Box 19, Item WG366)
    - Untitled - Five hunters who have killed a fowl, undated (Box 19, Item WG367)
    - Children at play. These children may not all be related. Corpus Christi, Texas, 1949 (Box 19, Item WG368)
    - Untitled - Two elderly men comparing timepieces in Denison, Texas, 1954 (Box 19, Item WG369)
    - Southeast Missouri Farms. Son of sharecropper combing hair in bedroom of shack. Reprint from Library of Congress, May 1938 (Box 19, Item WG370)
    - Farm children playing on homemade merry-go-round. Williams County, North Dakota, November 1937 (Box 19, Item WG371)
    - Farm children playing on homemade merry-go-round. Williams County, North Dakota, November 1937 (Box 19, Item WG371a)
    - Children in Nursery receiving Cod Liver Oil. Lakeview Project, Arkansas, December 1938 (Box 19, Item WG372)
    - Workers of the boot making shop, Alpine, Texas, May 1939 (Box 19, Item WG373)
    - Aged Mexican woman, Crystal City, Texas, March 1939 (Box 19, Item WG374)
    - Mother and child in front of shack in May's Avenue camp. Oklahoma City, Oklahoma. Refer general caption No. 21, July 1939 (Box 19, Item WG375)
    - Two young couples with their children these are migratory berry pickers near Ponchatoula, Louisiana, April 1939 (Box 19, Item WG376)
    - Wife of FSA client, Southeast Missouri farms, May 1938 (Box 19, Item WG377)
    - In front of movie theater. Chicago, Illinois, 1941 (Box 19, Item WG378)
  - Oversize Photographs, 1936-1961
    - Auction, Woodstock, New York, 1936 (Box 20, Item WG084)
    - Front entrance to Mexican home, San Antonio, Texas. This is home done hand work, 1939 (Box 20, Item WG149)
    - Mass meeting called to discuss ways and means for raising county fund in order to continue WPA (Work Projects Administration) roadwork. San Augustine, Texas, 1939 (Box 20, Item WG159)
    - Indians fishing for salmon at Celilo Falls, Columbia River, Oregon, 1941 (Box 20, Item WG273)
    - Blaine Sergeant, coal loader, on his way home after work. PV&K Coal Company, Clover Gap Mine, Lejunior, Harlan County, Kentucky, 1946 (Box 20, Item WG317)
    - Saudi Arabia [shot for Aramco], 1955 (Box 20, Item WG330)
    - Detail of nineteenth century home in Texas, 1961 (Box 20, Item WG344)
    - Woman and child, flood refugees in schoolhouse, Sikeston, Missouri, 1937 (Box 21, Item WG091)
    - A flood refugee and his family in the schoolhouse at East Prairie, Missouri, 1937 (Box 21, Item WG093)
    - Machinery against the garage on Matt Henry's farm near Tipler, Wisconsin. Note primitive scythe rake, 1937 (Box 21, Item WG094)
    - Saturday night in a saloon, Craigville, (Koochiching) Minnesota, 1937 (Box 21, Item WG099)
    - Mexican beer hall, Robstown, Texas, 1939 (Box 21, Item WG146)
    - Palma di Montechiaro (Sicily), 1960 (Box 21, Item WG333)
    - [Young girl on steps at] Children's Concert, Austin, Texas, circa 1950-1955 (Box 21, Item WG339)
    - Double muggers waiting for their turn at the rodeo [at the Texas Cowboy Reunion], Stamford, Texas, 1959 (Box 21, Item WG353)
    - Ralph Yarborough in Washington, D.C., [at the] Senate Commerce Committee, circa 1950-1960 (Box 21, Item WG364)
    - [Two young girls at] Yarborough Senate Campaign HQ, Austin, Texas, 1957 (Box 21, Item WG365)
- Paintings by Lee, circa 1930-1935
  The three oil paintings in this series are not dated, but were created during the early 1930s, when Lee studied painting in Woodstock, NY. A friend suggested Lee buy a camera and take photographs to improve his painting technique; Lee did so and quickly became interested in photography. The painting of the man in this series remains unfinished as a result of Lee's shift in artistic focus.
  - Man, unfinished, undated (Map-case Dr 5)
  - Young woman, undated (Map-case Dr 11)
  - Farm scene, undated (Map-case Dr 11)
- Artifacts, undated
  The bulk of this series is comprised of three of Russell Lee's cameras and their accessories, such as his hand-held flash and various viewfinders. Also included is Lee's Leitz 35mm enlarger, and his cap from his tenure with the Air Transport Command.
  - Contax camera and case
  - Araflex camera and case
  - Linhoff camera and case
  - Camera case used while in Air Transport Command, includes five notecards, three lightbulbs in boxes, and one empty lens box
  - Leitz 35mm enlarger